Vojtech Letal

About me

I am a machine learning engineer with rich experience including software engineering and applied research. During my career, I worked on several ML projects which taught me how to build a data processing pipelines and push models into production. I am writing production code mainly in Scala and most recently Python which allowed me to develop a deeper understanding of programming paradigms, data structures, and coding styles and find a passion for functional programming.

Email: letal.vojtech@gmail.com Tel: +420775330515 Github: letalvoj

Professional Experience

Staff Scientist, AI - Avast s.r.o. (Prague, Czechia)

04/2021-present

• Responsible for internal productization of a deep learning platform based on Mill.jl co-developed by Avast and CTU

Senior ML Engineer & Tech Lead - Blindspot.ai (Prague, Czechia)

09/2015 - 04/2021

- Leading a team of developers working on several analytical and ML tasks for a US-based cybersec startup
- Responsible for developing a real-time event-based anomaly detection platform
- Prototyped a regression model for the Czech presidential election which confidently predicted the outcome from less than 5% of early results
- Worked on toolbox designed to analyze correlations between crimes and external conditions like weather using data from a local police department

DS12 Resident - DataScience Inc. (Culver City, CA, USA)

summer 2016

- ullet 1 of 9 residents selected to participate in a 12-week elite, intensive residency program with 2.5% acceptance rate
- Developed a passion for FP concepts applicable to both Scala and other languages
- Implemented recommendation system with real client data using ALS and pattern mining in Spark
- Trained churn prediction model on real client data and identified several likely causes of churn
- Designed scalable production ETL pipeline which outperformed legacy SQL-based solution 6x (20 min) and was 36x (< 1\$) cheaper to execute

R&D - Cisco Systems (Prague, Czechia)

06/2014 - 08/2015

- Worked in a team which developed state-of-the-art anomaly detection system on network traffic data
- Implemented novel Bayesian inference algorithm to estimate probability of maliciousness of domains
- Extensively used big data technologies such as Twitter Scalding and Apache Spark

Education

Master's degree in Artificial Intelligence

09/2012 - 06/2015

Czech Technical University in Prague - Open Informatics (First-class honors)

Bachelor's degree in Communication technology

09/2009-06/2012

Czech Technical University in Prague - Communication, Multimedia and Electronics

Knowledge

Languages Czech (Native), English (Fluent)

Programming Python, Scala, Java, Bash, Git, PostgreSQL, C/C++ (basics), HTML+JS (scraping)

Frameworks Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Shapeless, Cats, Apache Spark, Apache Flink, Jupyter

DevOps CI/CD, Docker, Terraform, Ansible, Networking (basics)

Skills Data Analytics, Data Cleaning, Machine Learning, Statistical Modeling

Patents

Vojtech Letal, Tomas Pevny and Petr Somol. Discovering yet unknown malicious domains using relational data. US Patent App. 14/844,379.

Publications

Vojtech Letal, Tomas Pevny, Vaclav Smidl, and Petr Somol. Finding new malicious domains using variational bayes on large-scale computer network data. In *Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference, NIPS 2015 Workshop*, 2015.

Activities

Rock climbing, Yoga, Meditations, Reading, Traveling, Electronics, Biking, Parenting